okay let's get started
alright so today we're gonna talk about
Bayes nets also known as graphical
models which are a technique for
building probabilistic models over large
numbers of random variables in a way
that is efficient to specify an
efficient to reason over I think this is
a really exciting topic because this is
one of the main tools that we just
didn't have in the sort of first
go-around of AI and say the 80s and it's
not like people weren't aware of
probability it's not like people weren't
aware that there was ambiguity and an
uncertainty we just didn't have the
tools we needed to manage and reason
over uncertainty at scale and one of the
main tools that was developed was what
we'll be talking about today so in
general what we're talking about now is
probabilistic modeling and the first
part of the course we mostly talked
about actions selecting actions sequence
of actions chaining reasoning along
actions and what we're talking about now
is not so much about actions but about
beliefs so you want to be able to
describe how some portion of the world
some variables that you care about how
they work and in a probabilistic setting
variables work how variables work means
how they interact in a noisy way with
each other so this is modeling so
there's gonna be a whole bunch of math
we're gonna talk about the machinery and
the formalisms today but this is
modeling and whatever you do modeling
you're in the game of making
simplifications so models are always
going to be simplifications our
probabilistic models are going to be
simplifications so we'll pick some
random variables and then it'll be some
variables we don't model showing me some
variables they just don't appear either
because we don't want to take the time
to model them or we don't know how to
model them and it may be that even
amongst the variables we have there are
interactions that are too minor or too
expensive to capture so whenever we talk
about models there's sort of the
formulation of the model which variables
do I include which interactions will I
model where do I get those probabilities
and how do I learn them and that's
that's tricky often they're you're
making judgment calls and trade-offs and
then once you have your model
there's the algorithms and queries you
run against it
formal questions in this model what is
the probability of X given Y and that's
what we'll be starting to talk about
here and as we go we'll try to sensitize
a little bit the questions that occur in
terms of thinking of trade-offs I love
this quote from George box all models
are wrong but some models are useful and
our job is to come up with models that
are useful not really models that are
exactly right because only in rare cases
can we model a domain exactly and we'll
see examples of that today in the back
of your head sink what's the price of
not modeling a domain exactly the price
is uncertainty all the variables we you
leave out all the interactions you leave
out they show up as noise on the other
variables and we'll see examples of that
so what are we going to do with
probabilistic models remember this is in
the framework of rational AI which means
making decisions that maximize your
expected utility part of maximizing your
expected utility is inferring what's
gonna happen or inferring something
about underlying causes given evidence
and so we or really our agents need to
reason about unknown variables and that
usually takes the form of given some
things I do know my evidence and some
things I don't know but I'm curious
about the query variables and a model
that connects them what can I conclude
and that's we'll get into today one
example of this is explanation this is
diagnostic reasoning I see some symptoms
and I want to know the underlying cause
another example of this is prediction
this is causal reasoning I have a model
I think what will happen if I make this
change and then I play it forward okay
and that seems like a simulation and in
a way it sort of is noisy simulation
another kind of thing that we'll see
probably in about two weeks
another use we can use these
probabilistic models for is value of
information queries and that's for
things like remember in ghostbusters I
could probe and gather information or I
could act and there was a trade-off
between gathering information and making
a decision and so you have questions
like how much whether it's in dollars or
utilities how much value is there in
finding out this piece of evidence those
computations where knowledge is
associated with gains and utility are
really a fundamental thing in rational
decision-making and those are called
value of information computations
and we'll take a look at that once we
have all of the machinery and that's
gonna be I think a really cool lecture
where we connect the action
decision-making up to the probabilistic
inference okay any questions before we
get started okay so we're gonna in some
ways continue where we left off in the
past lecture talking about probabilistic
models which are formally joint
distributions of our collection of
random variables and talking about
properties of those models and
computations we can do over those models
one major property that's going to be
really important today that we didn't
get into last time is the notion of
independence between random variables
and then following on to that the more
important notion of conditional
independence so we say two variables in
a Joint Distribution are independent if
the following holds so informally two
variables are independent if there's no
interaction between them
that's an informal notion what does that
mean mathematically it means that if I
take a distribution P of XY and remember
that's a big table that tells you for
every value of x and y how likely that
outcome is and that's going to be the
probability of that outcome if for every
x and y the probability that x and y
happen together is simply the
probability that X happens nothing said
about Y times the probability that Y
happens nothing said about X now this is
in general doesn't hold right what do we
know in general we know in general that
P of X comma Y the probability of x and
Y is the probability of x times the
probability of Y given X right that's
always true that's the product rule okay
we saw that last time but you might have
a very special distribution in which Y
in fact doesn't depend on X at all and
the joint probability is equal to the
product of the marginal probabilities
what this says is that this joint
distribution which is a big
two-dimensional table factors into the
product of two simpler distributions
here two one-dimensional tables and that
means it's a special kind of simple
distribution here's another way you can
write that another way you can write
this is just what we showed up here that
if it's true that the joint distribution
factor since the product of the
marginals it's going to be true that for
all x and y the conditional probability
of accidence
given why that is how likely X is to
take a certain value given a value of y
is the same as its marginal probability
that is learning something about Y
doesn't change my belief in X at all and
if that's true then we say X and y are
independent we write that this way that
little thing between x and y you can
think of that as as a sort of
perpendicular sign it says there there
in some deep sense they're they're
independent they're doing their own
thing so that looks like a perpendicular
sign
okay now independence is our first
example of a modeling assumption I can
take two random variables like coin flip
1 and coin flip 2 and I can ask what is
their joint distribution or I can make
an assumption I can say you know what I
know enough about how coin flips work
that I'm going to assume they have
nothing to do with each other and I can
think of them as having as being
governed by independent distributions
with no interaction terms which means if
I want to know their joint probability I
multiply their independent probabilities
okay there's a couple reasons why
independence might not hold one is that
there are often very subtle interactions
or weaker interactions you may choose
not to model them but they're often
these sort of like lower order
interactions we'll see some examples of
that today and of course if you actually
look at a joint distribution that comes
from data often there's going to be
imperfect independents so if I flip
coins a couple of times they might not
exactly fall independently that would be
something that would only be true in the
limit so let's take an example and this
will do intuitively let's say we have a
domain which has the following random
variables whether so what kind of
weather is there traffic how much
traffic is there maybe that's been
discretized into light traffic and heavy
traffic cavity this represents do I have
a cavity in my mouth and toothache do I
have a toothache so here's four random
variables that I may care about and if I
build a probabilistic model over them we
might be able to simplify that model
instead of being a big four-dimensional
giant table I might be able to split it
into two tables where parts of my domain
don't interact so what's a good split or
maybe are all these variables maybe are
independent are there any variables
there that
probably aren't independent that's an
example of things that are not
independent one is weather and traffic
there's probably some correlation there
weather gets bad traffic gets bad ok
those aren't independent how about
cavity and toothache independent no go
through your dentist dependent all right
but these two subsets of variables maybe
don't have any major interactions and so
I might say that the variables weather
and traffic although they interact
together they may be governed by one
distribution cavity and toothache are
governed by another distribution and
there maybe don't need to be any
interaction terms so if I want to have
the probability overall for I can write
that as the product of the probability
of the two pairs okay that's the idea
behind independence let's do an example
here is a here is a joint probability
distribution over the variables T and W
from last time remember T was either hot
or cold it was the temperature and W is
either Sun or rain it was the weather
and here's some probabilities there are
many probability distributions over
these variables they all look just like
that but with different numbers and of
course they all have to one they're all
positive and that kind of thing now what
I can do is I can compute the marginal
over T so I can say well T is either hot
or cold and if I want to know what's the
total probability of T equals hot I look
at my joint table I look at all the
consistent rows and I add those together
and so I get point five and so I can
compute this we did this last time this
is projecting a joint distribution over
the two variables onto a marginal
distribution over just one and of course
I can do that for P of w2 and I look in
there and I do my computations and I see
the total probability of Sun is point
six for example okay so p1 here on the
left is a Joint Distribution over these
variables PT mpw are marginal
distributions of that joint distribution
so these are these are derived okay now
I can ask a question which is what is
the probability of
, son well I can look it up in my table
and p1 and ICO
it's point four so in p1 that's point
four in a distribution in which these
distributions p.m. PW were the marginals
and where independence held I would know
that P of hot comma Sun is equal to P of
hot the marginal times P of Sun and so I
can look those up
well here's P of hot here's P of Sun and
that's 0.3 what do we know we know that
p 1 is not a distribution in which T and
W are independent and in general things
aren't independent if I grab an
arbitrary probability distribution over
some variables things won't be
independent only a simple subset of them
are for example here's p2 in this one
P of hot comma Sun is 0.3 and if you
check all the other entries you'll see
that that definition of Independence
holds the product of the marginals is
equal to the joint for all of those
different outcomes okay so P 2 and B 1
just to sort of exercise some brain
muscles for next time P 2 and P 1 are 2
different joint distributions over the
same variables P 2 has the property that
T and W are independent P 1 does not
have that property so in some sense P 2
is simpler one way in which it's simpler
is I can write it by just applying U P
of T and P of W and giving you the
information that I'm thinking about the
independent distribution so it's more
compact any questions about that yep
okay so there's a couple of important
things here in Latin let me let me kind
of split them apart one I'm giving you
probability distributions I'm not
telling you what data you learn them
from or what sampling error there is or
any of that we will get to that later
right now there's these are simply two
probability distributions they have
different parameters one of them is
independent and I can verify that that's
p2 by checking these equality's and p1
is not independent and what that means
is T and W interact in p1 so for example
as we can see if hot and Sun don't
interact the probability of hot and Sun
is 0.3 hot and Sun do interact in p1 and
so probabilities 0.4 and so there's a
correlation there right and you might
informally say that correlation is it's
more likely to be hot if it's sunny okay
the sampling question is a good one and
we'll get to it later all right
here's an extreme example of
Independence let's say you are a octobot
and you're flipping a whole bunch of
coins and you're flipping end coins and
you want to describe this kind of
mathematically
imaginable giant joint distribution over
these n variables it's of size two to
the N because for every sequence of
heads and tails there at the end is the
probability but of course we know that
when you flip a coin you flip another
coin those things are independent and so
there's no need to actually ever write
down this giant exponentially large
distribution I can instead just write
down each of the N marginal
distributions and armed you with the
knowledge that in my model these random
variables are independent and then if
you ever ask me a question from the full
Joint Distribution we can just multiply
together the pieces and get the answer
okay in fact it could be even more
compact than this because in addition to
being independent these coins could also
be identically distributed which means I
only have to give you one probability
distribution and then you can imagine
replicating it okay but this already is
an exponential speed-up this thing on
the bottom of this is of size two
the N and this thing on the top is just
of size 2n so it's a lot better okay all
right so independence is great
it lets us take a multiplicatively large
table and break it into smaller pieces
this should maybe remind you of
something in CS Pease
how much easier those tsps were if I
could take my big CSP break it into
smaller csps
and solve them independently but we'll
bring back the mouse in a second but
just like in CSP is with where we talked
about if subproblems that completely
don't interact it's also the case that
independence probabilistically is very
rare and it's very rare for a couple
reasons one variables do tend to have
interactions but in particular when you
choose to build a model of something you
typically throw in all the variables
that you care about and those are the
variables that interact yes it's true
that weather and traffic don't interact
with cavity and toothache
but they generally don't show up in the
same model either so in general all of
your variables do have some degree of
interaction and independence is too
strong a notion but it's the building
block of something that we can use
efficiently which is called conditional
independence so in conditional
independence we don't go so far as to
say that two random variables have no
interaction what we say instead is that
their interaction is sort of mediated by
another variable and the way we write
that formally is rather than saying that
the Joint Distribution is a product of
marginals we have some other
simplification of the chain rule that is
less radical so for example if we take
the the variables okay so imagine you
are building a dentist robot okay and
it's going with this little probe and
it's it's poking at your teeth and the
random variables are do I have a
toothache or not do I have a cavity or
not and will that little probe catch on
a hole in your tooth so these are three
random variables and for three variables
I could imagine just having a full
distribution it wouldn't be that big but
I might be able to do better than that
okay because somehow it seems like
if I have a cavity my tooth might hurt
or it might not but if I have that
cavity whether or not the probe
physically catches on my tooth maybe
doesn't have much to do with whether or
not I'm feeling pain okay and if that's
the kind of simplifying assumption you
can use via conditional independence so
I could make an argument in this domain
that goes something like this if I have
a cavity the probability that the probe
catches and it doesn't depend on whether
or not I'm experiencing pain
what is that formally formally that's
saying the probability of plus plus
catch given the toothache and the cavity
is just the same as the probability of
the catch given the cavity somehow the
toothache doesn't add any information so
the condition the conditional
probability of catch given toothache and
cavity is the same as the conditional
probability of catch given just cavity
okay now in an actual joint distribution
this could be true or not you could go
check you could go turn some numbers in
check as a modeling assumption I could
say before I even get a probability
distribution
I want to assume this to simplify my
life and make my distribution more
compact now that same independence would
have to hold even if you don't have a
cavity so in this case well if I don't
have a cavity there's some probability
that the probe will catch anyway now the
question is what's the probability that
the probe will catch if I don't have a
cavity but for some reason I'm
experiencing tooth pain well you don't
have a cavity so who knows why you're
experiencing tooth pain and you might
make the assumption that those
conditional probabilities are the same
what does this mean this basically means
that once you know about cavity you know
all you need to about cash and the
toothache doesn't matter anymore is that
independence well it's not independence
because it's not the case that the catch
and the toothache are independent if
that were true if I learned that I had a
toothache it wouldn't change my belief
of whether or not the dentist would find
a catch but it should change my belief
right because the toothache maybe means
I have a cavity which in turn maybe
means that there's going to be a catch
but there's not a direct connection
that's formalized by these equations
what we say here is we say that the
random variable catch is conditionally
independent of toothache giving cavity
that's that's much weaker than being
completely or marginally or absolutely
independent of toothache it's only once
you know cavity there's no sort of
correlation left between them other than
what was mediated by that variable so if
these properties hold we say catch as
conditionally independent of toothache
and there's a bunch of ways to write
that statement which are all
mathematically equivalent conditional
independence is an assumption it may or
may not hold in a given distribution and
when you assume it you simplify your
distribution but that same assumption
can be written in a lot of ways one is
this way what's above that if units
catch giving cavity as the same as cache
giving cavity in toothache but you can
write it the other way you can say the
probability of toothache giving cavity
is the same as toothache giving cavity
and also knowing about the catch you can
also write it like this
I actually really like writing it this
way this way says that once I know the
the value of the cavity random variable
whether it's plus or minus the remaining
distribution over toothache and catch
that distribution is independent so
toothache and catch you can think of
that as its own little distribution over
two variables conditioned on cavity and
if that little distribution itself is
independent for that conditioning
environment then you have conditional
independence each of these can be
derived from the others you can go apply
your definition of conditional
probability and cross stuff out and show
that okay yep
it's a great question so does this does
the knowledge that let's write this
somewhere so I could write tooth ache is
independent of catch given cavity does
that imply the toothache and catch are
not independent
not necessarily I could go back to my
coin flips and I could say coin flip too
and coin flip for are independent yep
are they also conditionally independent
given coin slip three yes but you know
something stronger so in general we want
to use the strongest assumption we can
make but just because you have one
assumption doesn't mean that other
assumptions are not simultaneously true
okay so we already talked about this
unconditional or what's called absolute
independence is very rare on the other
hand conditional independence is one of
our most basic ways of saying something
about a probabilistic model that
simplifies it in a way that allows us to
track tably compute important quantities
on large distributions so can
independence rare and theoretical
conditional independence very important
okay and we'll see conditional
independence and its consequences a lot
today okay so mathematically if I have a
distribution of our three variables XY
and Z and I say X is conditionally
independent of Y given Z what that means
what that has to bottomed out is this
statement for all values of XY and Z so
you would have to check the whole
distribution you go now and check check
check check check check check or prove
it to yourself mathematically if you
want to verify this property holds on a
distribution so for all x y&z the
probability distribution over x and y or
the probability of x and y given z is
equal to x given z times y given Z so if
you ignore Z there that's independence
but since that independence only holds
when Z is known it's conditional
independence this is another way to
write it this says for all x y&z the
probability you're
leaf over ax given your knowledge of Z&Y
depends only on what you know of Z okay
this says that if you already know Z and
you have some belief over X and you
learn something about Y your belief
should not change okay all right let's
do some practice we're gonna come back
to these these toy domains I think three
times today depending on how far we get
so let's think about domain with the
following random variables traffic t
that's how much traffic there is
umbrella whether or not whether or not I
have an umbrella or whether or not I
observe an umbrella on my robot and then
raining whether or not it's raining so
are any of these things independent you
look and you say oh well the umbrella
and the traffic don't have any kind of
correlation well that doesn't sound
right because if I see the umbrella
I might think huh maybe there's gonna be
traffic too because maybe it's raining
okay so nothing's actually going to be
it's probably a too strong and
assumption and maybe not a useful
assumption to assume independence but
what could we assume is conditional
independent two variables that may
interact but that interaction is
completely mediated by a third any votes
yep
I guess I'm looking for a statement of
the form something is conditionally
independent of something else given some
third thing okay so that's the presence
of umbrellas and traffic on the freeway
are conditionally independent once you
know whether or not it's raining so
let's think what that means that means
if I know it's raining well there's this
traffic is likely and so are umbrellas
but not in a correlated way it's not
like when it's raining and the umbrella
comes out suddenly everybody's like
turning their head to see the umbrella
and that causes more traffic there's not
an additional correlation and you say
well wait but what you said is a little
weird but maybe possible yeah there's
always going to be um there's always
conceivable additional interactions that
you can declare two minor to be modeled
and of course we could quantify what two
minor to be modeled means in terms of
sort of information gain and things like
that but we're not going to do that
today okay so for today it seems
reasonable to say that traffic and
umbrella are not marginally independent
but they seem to be conditionally
independent given rain and that is an
assumption we can make to simplify our
model and you say well how exactly does
that simplify my model I thought you
were just handing me giant probability
distributions today we'll see how it
simplifies your model by allowing you to
specify it in a more compact way okay
okay let's do another one here's this
model F is whether or not there's fire s
is whether or not there's smoke in the
room and a is whether or not the alarm
goes off now on this one maybe it's
tempting to start thinking about things
causally which can be misleading but
often helpful anyway so let's think of
are there two variables that maybe have
some interaction but only mediated by
another one any one may want to make a
state an assertion that something should
be conditionally independent of
something else given a third variable
let's think let's first think about what
caricature I have of
robot fire alarm situation it's that the
standard way these things work is
there's fire or not and if there's fire
that fire has smoke and that smoke gets
into the alarm and the alarm has a smoke
sensor and goes off and maybe that's all
noisy process this alarm doesn't always
go off sometimes it goes off anyway okay
so now what can I say about these
variables like let's yep yeah so it
seems like a reasonable statement I
could say well the fire and the alarm
are certainly not marginally independent
that's the whole point of a fire alarm
is when the alarm goes off it makes you
worry that there's a fire that's a point
of the alarm but if the mechanism is via
the smoke then it may be that if I put
smoke into the room and I know I've put
smoke into the room now suddenly there
may be no additional correlation you say
well what if the fire alarm also had a
temperature sensor well ok then this is
a poor model now so here's an assumption
that may make sense to make or not based
on what is actually going on in the
world and how closely I want to model it
ok let's talk about how conditional
independence which so far has been a
relatively intuitive concept let's see
how that's gonna anchor into expressions
we can write about joint probability
distributions and ways we can write them
using the chain rule so remember the
chain rule says that if I have n
variables and I want to talk about the
probability of some assignment to those
n variables one way I can write that as
a product of other probabilities is I
can say well it's the probability of x1
taking on whatever value it takes on x
naught the probability of x2 by itself
but the conditional probability of x2
given x1 so given what I've already what
I already have at x1 I extend that text
to and similarly times the probability
of x3 given everything that precedes it
in that ordering of variables this is
always true and remember this was true
because you could think you know here's
probability of x1 but the probability of
x2 given x1 was just
P of X 2 comma X 1 divided by P of X 1
and then the the X 1 is cancelled in
this whole thing sort of telescopes so
that that's no assumption that's just
the chain rule that's always true and by
the time you get to the end to X n its
xn conditioned on all variables
preceding it so not super helpful ok so
the trivial decomposition here of
traffic rain and umbrella is that that
joint probability can be rewritten as
the product of probability of rain times
the probability of traffic given rain
times the probability of umbrella given
traffic and rain this is always true
over any distribution over three
variables but we decided something we
decided that for the purposes of our
model it seemed reasonable to assume
that the probability of umbrella given
rain and traffic was the same as the
probability of umbrella given just what
okay given just rain because umbrella
and traffic were conditionally
independent given rain and if we make
that assumption
now that joint probability is equal to
the product of these simpler conditional
probabilities and now we're starting to
get somewhere because now I have a way
of talking about it a large potentially
exponentially sized Joint Distribution
as a product of little pieces that don't
just keep growing and growing and
growing in the chain rule by the time
you get to the end these conditional
families are just as big as the Joint
Distribution but not anymore because
they're not getting more complicated as
I go ok so now I finally accomplished
something from the simplification which
is I can specify entries of a Joint
Distribution using products of simple
probabilities and how simple they are
depends on what conditional independence
assumptions I can make ok so we're gonna
do now is we're gonna get into Bayes
Nets which are also called graphical
models which are a tool to help us
express conditional independence
assumptions and think about the minnow
graphical way which can both help us
design algorithms and also help us sort
of think about these probability
distributions in new ways that has been
helpful all right
let's think about Ghostbusters so
remember this is the tiniest Ghostbuster
board it's got two squares that means
the ghost is in either the top square or
the bottom square so that's it so one
random variable is where's the ghost and
I could phrase that as ghost location or
true-false ghost is in the top that's
going to be the random variable G let's
say it's uniform marginally here's two
other random variables remember we took
sensor readings and let's let's imagine
the sensors just say red or not red
where red means close okay so I could
have random variables B and T which are
the reading in the top square it could
be red or not it's noisy the reading in
the bottom square it could be red or not
it's noisy okay and my sort of verbal
description of this model is each sensor
reading depends only on where the ghost
is what that means is the two sensors
they're certainly not marginally in
depending because if I reread up top I'm
probably not going to read right on the
bottom if I read red on the bottom I'm
probably not going to read right up top
so certainly not marginally independent
but it's reasonable to say that they're
conditionally independent given the
actual position of the ghost okay that
is if I know where the ghost is now
these are just noisy sensor readings
that aren't correlated and you say well
but they could be correlated because
what if your sensors sometimes busted
and then it reads red everywhere or what
if you know the first time you read red
it blows out the red light and now you
can't read red anymore somewhere else oh
you could imagine correlations but the
basic idea that there's an underlying
variable with independent measurements
seems appropriate for this domain so
what does that mean that means we're
given the following thing so I can tell
you oh hey the probability of the ghost
is in the top versus the bottom is 50/50
these are Givens I could also tell you
the probability of a red reading if the
ghost is at the top is 80 but the
probability of the probability of a red
reading given the ghost is in the bottom
is is only 40% okay so this does not
fully specify a joint distribution over
all these variables in general but it's
enough to specify the full joint
distribution if I have conditional
independence why is that that's because
if you come along and say hey I'm
curious about this entry of
joint distribution I have some value of
T B and G well in general I know that I
could look that up by telling you how
about I find P of G I have that here and
how about T given G okay I have that
here so far so good the chain rule
demands be given G and T that's what the
chain rule requires I don't have that so
I can't compute the this entry you asked
for in the joint distribution until
conditional independence for the rescue
if I assume that B and T are
conditionally independent given G being
the sensor readings are conditionally
independent given the ghost position
then I know that's the same as that
without the T and suddenly now I have
the right variable the right I started
the right parameter to plug in which
means with those Givens on the bottom
and the assumption of conditional
independence of the sensors now I can
fill out this whole table and now I can
do all of the computations that I did
last class like compute how likely is it
that the ghost is at the top given that
they both red red red or something like
that okay okay so Bayes Nets
what's the big picture yep
so are you asking how do I know that so
the assumption here that really let's
let's me go here is that is that T is
conditionally independent of B given G
are you asking how I know I have that
assumption or how does having that
assumption unlock the Joint Distribution
yeah so this is as modelers as modelers
we have to sort of take the information
we have about the problem which in this
class will usually be specified in words
like we'll give you some word problem or
appeal to some sort of fairly clear
causal structure where you can kind of
tell what is directly dependent on what
and translating that into conditional
independence so what I would so what I
would have to tell you is that I have to
tell you I'm imagining a case where I
have sensor readings and those sensor
readings are conditionally independent
given the underlying variable because
like I said if I could come up with some
story that makes that conditional
independence no longer reasonable to
assume so it's it another way to think
about it is the Givens are various
collections of conditional probabilities
along with conditional dependence
assumptions sometimes we state them in
word sometimes we'll just lay them out
in symbols and the point of this slide
is that when you have the right Givens
along with the right conditional
independence assumptions you've unlocked
the joint distribution you can build the
whole thing when you wouldn't have been
able to simply according to the chain
rule and that's really important because
it means that under the right
circumstances and with the right
conditional independence assumptions
tiny little pieces of probability
distributions can imply an entire joint
distribution which will unlock the
ability to take lots of little pieces
assemble them and reassemble them and
then produce some other little piece
without ever having to construct the
whole large object yep
so the question is why do we have so
much emphasis about finding the whole
joint distribution we won't forever but
right now the only algorithm we have for
answering an arbitrary query in a domain
is by starting with a joint distribution
and doing computation on it to answer
our query and so it's like tiptoeing
towards the ability to start with small
pieces build the whole joint
distribution and then collapse it again
into a different small piece where will
eventually get his algorithms that help
you avoid inflating the whole thing if
you don't have to and so you sort of
manage assembly and and projection in an
interleaved way and that's gonna be for
example the variable elimination
algorithm great questions more great
questions yes so conditional
independence is not an ordered notion
okay all right so what's the big picture
of Bayes nets and Bayes Nets are a
device for describing a complex
distribution over a large number of
variables where that large distribution
is built up of small pieces meaning
local interactions and the assumptions
necessary to conclude that the product
of those local interactions describes
the whole domain okay so it's going to
be our way of describing big complicated
domains using tiny pieces and there's
really sort of a deep analogy here to
CSPs where we described the interaction
amongst many many variables in terms of
lots of little local constraints that
didn't mean that are there weren't
correlations between what was assignable
at various places that were more distant
but what we described was the local
constraints and then there were global
consequences Bayes Nets are the same
we're gonna describe lots of little
local interactions and there's going to
be global consequences that will allow
us to do much more complicated kinds of
inferences okay so up till now as was
just pointed out we've been talking
about a probabilistic model being a full
Joint Distribution
mathematically that's great that full
joint distribution it's exponential in
size but it describes all the quantities
we care about but there's some there are
some major problems with using joint
distribution tables as models one is
it's too big to write down and
secondarily even if you could somehow
write it down it's really slow to do
computations over exponentially large
things okay
that's sort of a computational space and
time cost there's another cost which
which we don't always think quite as
much about in computer science but is
very important in AI and that is a
statistical cost the bigger a thing I'm
trying to learn the more parameters I'm
trying to learn you can think of the
parameters the entries of those
probabilities as being facts about the
world that I learned through observation
right the more parameters I'm trying to
learn the more data it will take to
learn that and so if I'm trying to learn
this really really large thing where
every row is sort of a its own its own
thing that must be learned that's going
to be very expensive whereas if I can
say that whole large object is really
described by a couple of simple
interactions that chain together now
suddenly I just have to learn those
pieces and things become much more
what's called sample efficient and
actually you'll see this in your your
projects already with reinforcement
learning where with with just naive cue
learning you have to learn about every
possible state of the world but with
function approximation you only have to
learn about the aspects of those states
that generalize in a much better way the
same kind of thing sort of Bayes Nets
based that's our technique for
describing complex joint distributions
which are models of a domain using
simple local distributions in this case
those will be conditional probabilities
these are also called graphical models
and what we do is we describe local
interactions between variables and we do
it in a very careful way that those
local interactions imply a distribution
over the entire set of variables we'll
be a little vague about those
interactions for a little bit and then
we'll get concrete okay so let's do some
Bayes Nets I'm gonna show you some
examples
then we're gonna think up some examples
and then I'll actually pull out a Bayes
net and we'll look kind of under the
hood and see what's really going on
so here is here's an example of a Bayes
net that describes an insurance domain
and so there's a lot of variables in the
insurance domain and of course one of
those things at the bottom are going to
be various costs that you might want to
predict if you're an insurance company
this
this one's for for vehicle insurance and
then there's gonna be various other
things like things you know like the age
of the driver and the mileage on the car
and there's gonna be things you don't
know like the skill of the driver or
whether or not there's an anti-theft
device or the socio-economic class or
something like that okay this Bayes net
is a description of that domain which
includes a decent number of variables
okay that's like you know something like
30 variables there and if each of those
variables had ten values like maybe ten
age buckets and ten mileage buckets or
something like that a full joint
distribution over all of those ten very
those thirty variables with ten values
each how many entries in that joint
distribution that's each each variable
has a choice of ten things so it's gonna
be ten to the 30th ten to the 30th
numbers is bad news okay but it's even
worse if you had to somehow like examine
10 to the 30th case studies in order to
figure out what those numbers even are
okay so Joint Distribution conceptually
really really big but with this this
Bayes net also shows is what the direct
interactions are so for example there
may be a correlation let's let's find
something interesting here let's think
if you're an insurance company let me
change colors if your insurance company
you might care a lot about this variable
accident that seems like something you
want to predict that's probably
correlated with the age of the driver
and in some way it's probably correlated
over with the year of the vehicle and
whether they have an extra car and what
their home zip code is and all of those
things but with this this network does
is it says actually you know what the
accident is really only directly
determined by the quality of the driving
and some factors about the car for
accident prevention like anti-lock you
know anti-lock brakes and and so on and
you say of course well how does that
connect to everything else with that
driving quality is determined by the
skill of the driver but also their risk
aversion like if you're a really good
driver but you take lots of risks that's
not the same quality of driving as if
you
a really good driver and you don't take
risks and so in specifying these little
pieces that can finally connect up to
things like for example the age or the
mileage on the car and so on okay so
this isn't the whole story for this
domain there's also the question of what
exactly is the dependence between age
and driving skill which isn't on the
slide and and I have no idea hopefully
some insurance company knows okay but
what this does is it lets us do things
like observe quantities like age and the
vehicle year and the zip code and
whether it has airbags and conclude
things like how likely is there to be an
accident okay that's one used for a
network like this and because all we
have are little local connections
between variables we don't need anything
so expensive as 10 to the 30th to
specify it okay this might be a network
that you use for simulation I know this
I know this is there gonna be an
accident and you're sort of computing on
the basis of evidence up here or initial
state up there you're computing what
might happen in with what probabilities
that's sort of computation going
downward in the network where you might
query something well in the network
here's an example where it might go the
other way you want to be you want to
have a robot mechanic and so there's
going to be evidence down at the bottom
of the network here and some underlying
causes of why the car might not start
like the battery could be dead or the
alternator could be broken and so you
might do things like you know diagnose
like are the lights is there an oil
light on what does the gas gauge read
was the battery meter read will a car
start and so on and so what you can do
in this network here is you observe some
of these things at the bottom and you
can do some inference over what causes
there might be now rather than exactly
knowing the probability of any mapping
from causes to effects we only know
little things like well when there's no
oil the oil light turns on except when
there's no power coming from the battery
or something like that and so a network
like this can help us do diagnosis and
also importantly it can encapsulate a
lot of knowledge about cars this network
probably knows more about cars than I do
that's maybe more comment on me
okay so graphical model notation water
graphical models it's gonna look a lot
like csps water graphical models well
they have nodes in them they're gonna be
graphs they're gonna have nodes in them
those nodes represent variables and
those nodes those variables have domains
and they can be unassigned which is
called unobserved or they can be
assigned which is called observed just
like in csps there are arcs and the arcs
represent interactions between variables
again just like CSPs CSPs we would say
something like hey these two variables
this one has to be greater than that one
I'll put a constraint between them it
may have other effects when it chains
together with other constraints but
that's my local interaction there's
going to be local interactions here and
we'll see in a bit what those local
interactions are okay the arcs indicate
something like direct influence between
variables formally they're encoding
conditional independence okay but it can
be very convenient to build up your
intuition to think about the arcs as
encoding encoding causality we'll see
that that's not actually true they don't
actually need to and they're not
guaranteed to encode causality but often
that's what ends up happening so here's
an example of a Bayes net for a model we
already know for cavity - faking catch
we see there's a direct influence
between cavity and toothache and another
direct influence between cavity and
catch but no direct influence during
toothache and catch the influence
between toothache and catch is mediated
by the path that goes to cavity and
paths in this graph are going to be very
closely related to conditional
independence so nodes and arcs nodes are
variables arcs are interactions for now
think of the area wills variables well
for now think of the arrows as causes
cavities cause tooth aches and they also
cause caches but tooth aches don't cause
caches and so I don't have an arrow
there okay I think we're gonna do is
we're gonna take a two-minute break now
and then we will come back and see
examples of first simple and then
increasingly complicated Bayes nets and
then we'll peek underneath the covers
and see what those Bayes nets are
defined by an addition to the graph okay
two minutes
okay let's see some examples of Bayes
Nets okay first one back to our
independent coin flips and independent
coin flips with no interactions between
the variables we're gonna have absolute
independence and the Bayes net that
corresponds to that will be a bunch of
variables with no arrows between them
okay as we'll see later when we dig a
little deeper into this disconnected
things in the network just like they
didn't see SPS correspond to
independents of problems and here that
means absolute independence okay here's
a simplified traffic domain variables
are is it raining T is there traffic so
what might we do well here's one
graphical model here's one Bayes net
over those variables this is the
independent one this one says in my very
simple model these two variables don't
interact so they're gonna each it turns
out have a marginal distribution and
that's all you know here's another model
in this model I have an interaction this
model says there's R and there's T and
the behavior of T is now a function of
the behavior of R so we are now
capturing in this model and I'll be
precise in in a bit how that's captured
we're now capturing a direct interaction
between R and T okay
they are both valid graphical models or
Bayes Nets over this domain but model
two is probably better the reason why
models two is better is because an agent
that's armed with model two can do
things like see traffic and conclude
something about rain or see rain and
conclude something about traffic once
you start taking too many arrows out as
you gather evidence you don't actually
have the ability to update your belief
over variables that you're care about
through connections to the evidence and
that's sort of the whole point you want
to see evidence and then infer something
about other variables all right let's do
a bigger traffic case this is gonna have
more random variables and we will build
a graphical model as we go as I draw
this model I'm not being precise yet
about the mathematical semantics of the
model we'll get that in a couple slides
for now just think about the arrows
being causal or direct influence all
right so let's add some variables to our
traffic model first variable traffic
okay I'll stick that there there's
either traffic or there's not second
variable rain where should that go
should be separate should a point to
traffic should traffic point to rain
think causal for now does traffic cause
rain or does rain cause traffic to the
best of my knowledge the rain causes the
traffic okay low pressure the barometer
has a low pressure reading what do you
think okay we can put L up here at
pointing terrain well it's certainly
correlated now you could be like wait a
minute a reading on my machine doesn't
cause it to rain so there's actually
these the actual low pressure then
there's the reading of the low pressure
which actually is L pointing to that
thing so we could get more and more
fancy but imagine this is the actual low
pressure on this guy all right my roof
is dripping how does that fit into all
of this so it seems like rain causes
that all right does anything else cause
that does the low pressure cause my roof
to drip hmm kind of I mean let's it's
like really low pressure like rips the
membrane off my roof or something like
it's that that's but that's mediated by
the rain
similarly like just traffic caused my
roof to drip like probably not less so
this is a reasonable model there's a
ball game how does that interact with
any of this
alright so ball game causes traffic any
other interactions certainly doesn't
cause my roof to drip anything else this
is reasonable yeah yeah it seems
reasonable to so here's an arrow that I
could include or not that would be a
modeling assumption it seems reasonable
that rain effects whether or not the
ball game happens if I emitted that I
would have a slightly simpler model and
there's always a trade-off between how
powerful your model is and how hard it
is to work with okay cavity
how about cavity
I was probably just out there somewhere
right it's probably like that's a
separate process
it's the dental process over there okay
all right
are there other graphical models I could
draw yes as I move arrows around and
delete them the set of conditional
independence assumptions changes and the
set of probabilities I need to specify
the behavior of the model will change to
before I had this
let me change its color before I had
this green arrow here I didn't have the
burden of specifying how ballgame
relates to rain and now I do on the
other hand now my models a little bit
higher resolution okay alarm Network
here's the deal the variables are there
may or may not be a burglary
let's stick that in here somewhere okay
my burglar alarm goes off where does
that go with respect to B well they seem
correlated and if we're gonna go in the
causal direction maybe the burglary
causes the alarm what about my neighbor
Mary calls okay let's let's put Mary
over here is that connected to all of us
well it depends right we're now making
assumptions about the model but what is
what are some reasonable ones okay one
is Mary's completely mary's in France
she just calls sometimes this is
appropriate now she may or may not call
it's disconnected might be that she
calls if she hears the alarm it might be
that she's like staring at my house
through her window and she'll see the
actual burglary and she might call even
if there's no alarm if there's a
burglary then I need an extra arrow okay
here's John calls so that's another
variable that may also be called because
of because of the alarm itself but if
Shawn's calling because Mary calls John
first before she calls me then I need
another arrow from m2j earthquake
where's earthquake Oh
we would have to say what we're assuming
about this one answer is the earthquake
can set off the alarm and only because
of the alarm do my neighbors call me
another could be earthquake directly
causes everybody I know to call me and
then there would be direct arrows from
you to jnm okay so you see the sort of
the these are modeling choices in this
class we have to give you a model or
clearly state the assumptions and say
draw the model and then we have to
compute with it
okay all right so now we're is a key bit
we're to the semantics of a Bayes net so
what's this about we just saw a sort of
intuitive example of building at least
the graph part of a Bayes net and
thinking about arrows as capturing
direct influence and now we're gonna
talk about is for a given Bayes net what
does it mean what joint probability
distribution does it encode and how do
we know that so here we go the full
definition a Bayes net is a set of nodes
one per variable X okay so every
variable in the network every variable
in the graph is is a variable in the
joint distribution I have a directed
acyclic graph over those nodes so there
arrows between them and there are no
cycles if you think about that
intuitively for causality that makes a
lot of sense like you don't have like
the rain caused the traffic and the
traffic caused the ballgame the ballgame
caused the rain that would be very
confused but we'll see mathematically
that this ACE duplicity meaning there
are no directed cycles in the graph
bottoms out in the chain rule it's
because in the chain rule you introduced
variables one kind of one at a time in
some order the fact that your graph has
no cycles means there is an order that
corresponds to the network okay so a set
of nodes a set of arrows between the
nodes that have no cycles in them and
hidden inside each node is a little
conditional distribution family so if
you peek inside a node there are a bunch
of conditional distributions that
describe the probability of that
variable as a function of its parents
meaning for every setting of the parent
values there's a distribution so if I
look at this node X
I see it has these parents a one through
a n that means if I peek inside X
there's a probability distribution over
X but not just one there's one for every
setting of the parents a so if you have
a lot of parents there's a lot buried in
this node so the more parents you have
the amount that you have to stuff in
that node to describe what X is going to
do as a function of the parents it grows
exponentially okay we often see this
abbreviation CPT is a conditional
probability table that's what lives in
the nodes you can think of this as a
description of a noisy causal process it
says what is X gonna do given a 1
through a n so you might things like
what is a causal process if it rains
then there's traffic ok we could do that
with with with logical rules but here
it's more like if it rains then there's
a 90% probability of traffic if it
doesn't rain there's a 30% probability
of traffic and because we need to
specify the response of a random
variable for each conditioning
environment of the parents we can think
of this as a noisy causal process okay
so a Bayes net is a topology meaning our
graph plus all the little local
conditional probabilities that live
inside the notes ok we'll see some
examples and then we'll build one of our
own any questions yep
it's a good question so the question was
couldn't you also express that one
variable makes another less likely you
can express any conditional relationship
so you could say that rain mates traffic
more likely you could say brushing teeth
makes cavities less likely but in
general things aren't boolean so you
could also say that the driver being of
age 20 to 30 changes the driving quality
distribution in the following way it's
an arbitrary relationship between the
parents and the distribution over the
child and that's actually important okay
it's important because all these arrows
tell you is sort of that there is a
conditional probability table for each
of these values it doesn't tell you
which table so when I draw an arrow
between rain and traffic in a network if
I draw an arrow between rain and traffic
that tells you that this this note can
can encode a different value for T given
each value of R it might encode that
rain makes traffic more likely it may
encode that rain makes traffic less
likely in fact there's even a setting of
the values for which it encodes that
they're actually independent and you
just can't tell from the graph because
for every value of R in fact it's the
same distribution over T yep
can you have an XOR relationship between
the parents and the children absolutely
you can have a noisy exclusive or right
so so like if it's a 1 through a N and I
want to say X is basically is exactly
one of them on I would have a whole
bunch of settings of a1 through an and
for a bunch of them X would probably be
on maybe probability 0.99 and for all
the rest X would probably be off and
whether it was or 1 or point zero zero
one or point three or whatever now the
details of the noise in that exclusive
Ward process but yeah and you can put
deterministic things in there if I want
to say rain causes traffic I peak in
here and well what is the probability of
traffic given that there is rain well
okay it's
you know plus T could be 1.0 minus T
could be zero or I could say no it's
noisy 0.9 point one or it's noisy 0.5
0.5 or whatever okay so there's the
topology which tells you what
relationships can exist and then there's
the actual numbers you stuff in which
are very important to they give you
things like what are the qualitative
interactions positive interaction
negative interaction yes
the question is what do you do if you
have two variables so you got a and B
here and that you would like to describe
a correlation between them but there's
no obvious causal interaction between
them or if there is maybe it feels
cyclic well it turns it's gonna turn out
that either the arrow in this direction
or the air in that direction gives you
the ability to specify any joint
distribution over those two variables so
the direction of the arrow is only going
to matter when it starts interacting
with other arrows in this case that's a
very good example of why it is that
these arrows are not causality because
there are plenty of cases where you have
two variables that have a non-causal
correlation graphical models are
perfectly adequate to express that but
the arrow stops sort of having this
intuitive meaning and they become a
little harder to think about as a great
question anything else all right all
right
so probabilities in a Bayes net a Bayes
net implicitly encodes a joint
distribution so I just told you what it
was it's a collection of variables they
have parents and there's little
conditional probabilities hiding under
each node they implicitly encode a joint
distribution according to the following
definition if you multiply together all
of the little conditional distributions
one for each node you're going to get
the following expression it's going to
be a product over all the nodes of a
probability of that node given its
parents okay by definition that product
of local probabilities in a Bayes net is
what defines the joint probability over
all of those variables and if you squint
at that right-hand side thing it looks a
lot like the chain rule probability of
each thing given some other things but
it's not the full chain rule and all of
the variables that are missing represent
conditional independence assumptions so
here's an example cavity causes
toothache cavity causes catch so what is
the probability of Plus cavity plus cash
but minus toothache well I don't know
but living in this node sorry living in
this node is probability of plus catch
and living in this node here for
toothache is probability of what is it -
toothache given plus catch and living in
the sorry rewind living under the cavity
known as probability of + cavity living
in the catch node is probability of +
catch given + cavity and probability
under the tooth decay under the tooth
ache node is probability of - toothache
given + cavity so I have all the P DS
pieces and what I know is that this
entry by definition of this Bayes net is
the probability of + cavity x + catch
given + cavity times probability of -
tooth given + cavity each of those terms
lives in the Bayes net when I multiply
them together in general the chain rule
says that's not the chain rule who knows
what you're gonna get okay
multiply those together at your own risk
the Bayes net comes with a guarantee
that when you multiply them together
you'll get the joint and that's because
it also comes with conditional
independence assumptions that we'll find
out about probably in the next lecture
okay why are we getting guaranteed
that's that just defining an entry of
the joint P of x1 through xn as the
product of all of the bits I have in my
Bayes net nodes given their parents'
results in a proper joint distribution
well the chain rule says that would be
okay if each if each variable was
condition not on its parents but on
everything before it in an ordering its
parents are a subset of things that are
before it in any topological ordering of
that graph and so we have the additional
assumption that P of each variable given
the ones preceding it is equal to P of
that variable just given its parents so
this is where that assumption comes in
all right
this means that not every Bayes net can
represent every joint distribution so if
I give you a Bayes net that looks like a
and B I can represent choice
distributions over the variables a and B
but not all of them just which ones just
the ones in which a and B are
independent if I don't want to represent
ones in which they're not I need to
throw some arrows on all right more
Bayes nets here's the coin flip Bayes
net but in addition to having each
variable be independent here I also know
that living under each variable is a
probability distribution governing that
variables response for each setting of
the parents no parents so marginal okay
that means probability of heads heads
tails heads is this probability of heads
times this probability of heads times
the probability of tails times the
probability of heads okay so to get an
entry of the joint distribution I
multiply all of the appropriate pieces
of the conditional probabilities each
variable will have one term in this
product okay and what's that gonna be
it's gonna be one half to the fourth
okay this Bayes net here I can fiddle
around with these point fives I can be
like oh x1 always comes up heads and x2
comes up heads point two of the time I
can fiddle with these probabilities all
day I can change the Joint Distribution
but try though I may I can never
represent a joint distribution in which
the variables are not independent I can
do one where they're not identically
distributed but not one in which they're
they're not independent okay here's our
traffic node or here's our traffic Bayes
net it's got a node for R and a node for
T and we know that living under R like
if you say what are you dreaming of node
R it's dreaming of this distribution
here which is some distribution over R
given its parents it doesn't have any
parents okay and in this case it rains a
quarter of the time what's living under
node T it is conditional probabilities
of T for every setting of the parent in
this case R and so it might be these
conditional probabilities T is off and
on when R is on and it's 50/50 when R is
off so given armed with this Bayes net
here if
I say well in the joint distribution
that Bayes net represents what is
probability of plus R and minus T I go
through and say well plus R that belongs
to the our network or the R node in the
network and then for plus R minus T is
right here so I will multiply together
those things and I will get 1/4 times
1/4 okay
or put another way I will multiply
together probability of plus R times
probability of minus T given plus R
which will be 1/4 times 1/4 okay here's
my alarm Network now suddenly we have a
network that's not just one or two
variables and I can compute under this
assumption that I have this topology
right the burglary causes the alarm and
the alarm causes John and Mary to call
but independently if you just tell me
the right probabilities under living in
each node I can compute a probability of
any event so for example you might tell
me well the probability of burglary is
point zero zero one and the probability
for earthquake is point zero zero two
and here is the response of the alarm
for all the different scenarios you know
like man I have to say what the alarm
does if there's a burglary and once the
alarm does with an earthquake and also a
burglary and an earthquake and also no
burglary or earthquake well when you
start giving those lots of parents
suddenly you have to describe how what
that node does in a bunch of different
conditioning environments so here it is
and you can see these are a bunch of
distributions over a here's one
distribution over a if there's a
burglary and an earthquake ninety-five
percent of the time the alarm goes off
here is the probability of the alarm
going off given just the burglary just
the earthquake neither burglary no
earthquake and of course Mary and John
have their own distributions which say
is how likely they are to call both in
the alarm scenario and in the non alarm
scenario these we either have to be
learned from data or just supplied as
Givens right now I'm giving them to you
as Givens and if I wanted to know for
example the probability that there was a
burglary and an earthquake but no alarm
and but John and Mary called anyway I
would go through and start multiplying
together the appropriate conditional
probabilities and that would define the
entry of the joint distribution
okay any questions on that and then
we'll do a couple quick extensions and
take a look at a demo all right so um
this gets the question before of
causality what if causality is not you
know it is not what your modeling codes
so right now this is the rain and
traffic this is the causal direction
rain causes traffic there's an arrow
from art to tea that means living under
the node R is the distribution over R
not conditioned on anything because R
doesn't have any parents and living
under T is a distribution over T but not
just one I have to give you a
distribution over T for raining and
another one for not raining and then I
can use that that formula which says
multiply all the entries together that's
like the Bayes net reconstitution
formula to take these pieces and define
this whole joint distribution in this
case the joint distribution is actually
just the same size as the conditionals
but see there's only savings when these
networks get big okay so here is the
joint distribution over TN r that is
implied by the Bayes net on the left
okay great so for example if I want this
entry I multiply the probability of plus
R times the probability of plus T given
plus R and I get 3/16 all right let's
flip it around
here's another Bayes net in this one
there's a variable T and there's a
variable R there's an error from T to
are like wait a minute traffic doesn't
cause rain the Bayes net does not care
whether traffic causes rain it is a
graph you put an arrow it's happy okay
but when you put that arrow you have to
supply conditional probabilities so what
lives under T well it used to be sort of
T as a function of R but now it's not
now it's just T there's some probability
of traffic and now under R I have to
specify how likely rain is given traffic
and how like the rain is given not
traffic okay those numbers exist let's
imagine this is those numbers and for
these particular numbers if I use the
Bayes net reconstitution formula and I
compute every entry of and look like an
arrow every entry of the joint
distribution
we'll be this one and if you're a really
good memory you'll remember this is
exactly the same Joint Distribution as
before so this network here which does
not match the causal process encodes the
exact same Joint Distribution over those
variables as the previous one now you
might like the previous one better and
there's a lot of advantages to drawing
these things causally but mathematically
it is just an expansion of the chain
rule and P of T times P of R given T and
P of R times P of T given R are both in
general for any distribution just going
to be the joint until you start getting
three or more variables or there's no
arrows you don't actually have any claim
about the underlying distribution okay
just talking about causality a bunch of
times when your Bayes net reflects the
true causal patterns they're usually
simpler that's just a fact about the
world and how we build these models
they're usually easier to think about
and they're a lot easier to elicit from
experts like it's way easier to go to a
doctor and say what fraction of people
who have strep throat have a fever
than it is to say what fraction of
people who have a fever have strep
throat like I don't know there's a lot
of reasons you could have a fever and
and it's a lot harder to get things in
the diagnostic direction usually
forgetting them from data this may not
be true anymore Bayes Nets don't have to
be causal sometimes there is no causal
net so like the example you gave or when
variables are missing often the
remaining variables are kind of
complicated from a causal standpoint so
for example traffic and drips in our
traffic model they're sort of correlated
by the underlying variable rain but they
don't neither really causes the other
so either direction of the arrow is fine
mathematically and then you end up with
arrows that reflect correlation but not
causation so what are these arrows mean
they might happen to encode causal
structure it's great when they do it's
intuitive but they really encode
conditional independence they encode
that when you write out the chain rule
in general you get P of X given all the
variables that precede it but now we
have P of X given only its parents so
it's a statement
that once you know the parents you don't
need to know the other things that
precede it and we'll unpack that a
little bit in the next lecture
okay so let's peek inside a Bayes net
let's build one all right
let's build a Bayes net let's create
some nodes let's do mr. traffic all
right let's build a node rain rain
I'll let it stay true or false there's
rain there it is all right let's make
more of a Bayes net we decided rain
causes traffic okay rains causing
there's rain there's traffic let's
create an arc from rain to traffic let's
make some more let's let's do some some
more what else was in this thing
there was like rain also causes drip my
roof drips rain causes drip what else we
had low pressure right low pressure
okay and that causes rain okay
I've drawn a graph in order to specify a
Bayes net and thereby a distribution
over these variables I need to do more
than that I need to actually give
probabilities for example how likely is
it that there's low pressure I don't
know maybe 0.1 now I need to say how
likely is it that there's rain well it
depends it's got a parent it's got low
pressure maybe when there's low pressure
it rains nine ninety percent of the time
and when there isn't low pressure it
rains one percent or ten percent the
time okay I could put in other numbers
I'm just making stuff up okay what lives
under drip this is the noisy
specification of how rain leads to drip
or how rain causes drip okay maybe
eighty percent of the time when it rains
it drips
and it almost never drips otherwise I
didn't put a zero there cuz that's just
a no-no in building Bayes Nets all right
how about traffic I need to describe the
dependence of traffic on its parent well
when there's rain there's 80% traffic
and when there's no rain there's 30%
traffic okay I have a Bayes net what can
I do with this Bayes net well I'll ask
it a couple quick questions like hey
what's the probability that there's
traffic 39 percent all right let's get
some observation what's the probability
that there's traffic given that my roof
is dripping should be higher or lower
than thirty-nine percent higher this is
higher this is lower well this is spent
let's find out it's higher and that's
because drip means it's probably raining
which means more likely to get traffic
let's make another observation let's
actually observe rain let's do a query
is traffic gonna go up or down now 79 -
8 it went up a little bit all right
here's the important one I know it's
dripping I know it's raining there's an
80% chance of traffic I discover that
there is a low-pressure system what will
happen to my 80% chance of traffic it
stays the same and that's because low
pressure only informs whether or not it
rains and I already know it's raining I
can't know it any more than I already do
and so they're disconnected in some way
and that must have something to do with
conditional independence we'll find out
what next week ok so let's just stop
there and we'll see you next week for
inference and Bayes Nets